Okay. Well thank you so much.
Those are amazing presentations.
I'm really happy to be here.
And today I'm really happy to be talking
about generative poetics
in the context of Japanese poetry,
something that hasn't
received much attention in scholarship
in any language, really.
And it's been something that in my own
field of like Japanese literary
studies, I've been claiming we all need
to pay more attention to this stuff.
And it feels like in the last few years
with what's happened with generative AI,
it kind of feels like a finger of a
monkey's paw has curled a bit
even worse.
It's kind of an AI generated monkey's paw
that has a few too many fingers.
But in any case, the connection
between writing and generation
has now, in the popular imaginary, largely
been conflated to certain types of LLM
based production,
and many have discussed the normal
devising forces inherent
to these kinds of text generation.
From my perspective, coming from Asian
studies, I also want to start
today's talk off by talking a bit
about some specific,
kind of unsettling aspects
of the marketing and use of generative AI,
specifically in relation
to popular conceptions of East Asia, East
Asia, and specifically, especially Japan,
often becomes kind of the imaginary.
That is the general test case to show off
the technology to Western audiences.
For example, in 2024, OpenAI premiered
its text to video model Sora, quote
named after the Japanese word for sky, to
signify its limitless creative potential.
And this Tokyo walk was one of their
very first preview videos.
So the products of generative AI
and the discourses around the technology
both fall with alarming regularity
into orientalist
and techno orientalist tropes about East
Asia.
In cases like Sora, Japan is ultimately
an inherently general, always othered
with dehumanized non people,
especially the central female figure
who's striding through a cityscape
filled with lit signs featuring
nonsensical fake Asian characters
like that's not real writing
as if to say, kind of, it's Japan
as long as you don't look too closely.
Because why would you look too closely?
Because it's obviously Japan.
Public discourses around the use of AI
to fall into yet more pernicious
orientalist tropes of East
Asians as copying unoriginal
or artificial or deceitful.
One prominent example of
this is the global media furor
that emerged around 2023.
Novel Sympathy Tower Tokyo Tokyo,
which won the Akutagawa Prize, Japan's
most prestigious award
for literary fiction, and for the novel,
which is kind of about AI in many ways.
She used ChatGPT to create the responses
when the character spoke to an in-universe
chatbot, totaling about maybe
one page of text drought the whole novel.
But the headlines around the world
frame things quite differently,
as if he had hidden her process
and tried to get away with something.
Winner of Japan's top literary
prize admits she used ChatGPT novelist
Rakuten wins fans most prestigious
literary prize than reveals she used.
ChatGPT, the winner of a prestigious
Japanese literary award, has confirmed.
AI helped her write her book and novel,
written with the help of ChatGPT,
wins top Japanese literary prize.
Here's how the author justifies it.
So you see this kind of rhetoric
that comes up a lot,
but I haven't given up hope on how
the generative can still be generative
for thinking about Japanese literature.
And but it's mostly in the realm of poetry
and of generative poetics writ large.
And I found the most success
in communicating the value
to people in my field
about thinking about the stuff seriously,
about the limits and affordances
of text generation, and also reasserting
that the story of these technologies
and the conversations around
them is a genuinely global
one, rooted in a variety
of experimental literary practices.
So today, I'm spending the rest of my time
thinking about the earlier history
of poetry generators
in Japan and of Japanese poetry,
finding predecessors that,
unlike the dominant uses of generative
AI on major platforms,
centered diverse kinds of legibility,
human agency, and and interestingly
open and contestable take on literary
ness and centering approaches
that value serendipity,
surprise, self-examination,
and a constant questioning of how we could
and should be implicated into technology
and it into us.
But this has a long history.
Thinking about, and even being anxious
about the general ability
of Japanese
poetry is not a recent phenomenon.
It kind of has its roots
in the 19th century.
There's a great recent book
by Scott Mill called The Ends of Meter
in Modern Japanese Poetry,
and he highlights how Marcel,
who's the progenitor of modern haiku
as we know it,
he came up with the word haiku,
pretty much,
and his mathematical anxieties
about foreign poetry.
So in 1892
he writes this a certain contemporary
scholar conversant with mathematics
that says it is evident from the theory
of permutations that there is
a numerical limit to the tanka
and haiku of Japan, which are confined
to a mere 20 or 30 syllables.
In other words, sooner or later the tanka
and haiku will reach their limit.
You may ask if that is so, when will
the end come for the haiku and tanka?
And I reply, I can't.
Of course, predict
the time of their total extinction.
But speaking approximately, I think
the haiku has already played itself out.
Even assuming that the end is yet to come,
we can confidently expect it
to arrive
sometime during the Meiji period, i.e.
by the 1920s or 1930s.
So he thought haiku was so short
and there are so few syllables
that we are running out of haiku.
And this is a crisis.
Mail points out that the
actual number of possible 17 syllable
haiku in Japanese is about 26 octillion.
So I think we're okay
for a little bit longer, but
this is an early example of the fears
about generative foreign poetry.
The idea that the form is so limited
that it only has so many permutations
and will eventually exhaust itself.
And embedded in this
more subtly, is a kind of anxiety
about the role of the human
in poetry making,
that if there are a set number of haiku
and tunc out there
that are merely to be selected
from existing ingredients,
the human is just there to curate
or slap things together.
And this kind of curation of preexisting
ingredients became computationally,
literally, as early as 1967, when Margaret
Masterman and Robin MacKinnon
would created their computerized
haiku program, which premiered
to great acclaim in the Cybernetic
Serendipity exhibition in London in 1968.
So the brevity and strong
constraints of the haiku, both formally
and in terms of subject matter,
lend themselves really well
to this kind of test case for generation
in a way that was a lot more nuanced
and a lot less creepy than that Sora video
I showed you, and that it actually
is grappling with the specific specificity
of the poetic form.
Masterman was just as interested
in understanding haiku better as she was,
and using haiku as a way to help people
understand computers better.
So in one interesting
and complicated quote from her,
the fact that the difficult problem
of producing a poems
generating formula was for the first time
made explicit by a rudimentary generating
formula being actually
displayed, explains the haikus
unexpected success at this exhibition.
People who are neither Japanese
nor poets could and did work
the algorithm and produce a poem,
which then in some cases
they carefully treasured and placed
in their breast pockets within Japan.
There is also an important
and fascinating legacy of work poetry,
generators and critical writings
about them starting in the 1970s
that want to pretty quickly
go through here, just to show you
some of the range and complexity
of what has been done.
Mizutani haiku making computer haiku.
Tsugaru from 1979, was an early experiment
on the Toshiba
Aiko's 600 that he saw as once again
not just a way to generate haiku,
but to contribute
strongly to our understanding of haiku.
In the process of creating a program
like this and interacting with it.
Speculating on the future of Computer
Haiku in 1984
holds out hope that something
unexpectedly amazing might happen
once this kind of haiku generation
becomes the norm.
How many verses he said brilliant,
baffling or clichéd might be generated?
The verses can be calculated
in an instant,
but what kinds of images or what
kinds of appearances might such work
take that we cannot predict?
There's only a vague premonition
that, suddenly or unexpectedly,
a strikingly vivid wonder might appear.
So he's emphasizing
the possibility of surprise, even
for the poet themselves,
and he links the specific worldview
to the worldview of haiku poetics,
like what's inherent to how haiku work?
Quote.
It comes down to the belief
that poetry should not be created through
meaning,
nor should it be read through meaning.
This notion has been a commonplace in
the world of haiku for a very long time.
End quote.
So a lot of haiku poets
now, especially in Japan,
say that the idea of a poem with an inner
meaning is kind of an imposition
from Western poetic concepts onto haiku,
which are meant to be much more about
impressions and moments and sensation,
and not about quote unquote meaning.
Suzuki Shiro Yasu.
Around the same time, in his 1985 poem
machine turned to free verse,
generating poems using a computer
based on audience suggestions,
noting that, quote, people tend to think
that poems are created in a closed room,
but when you do it in a public place
and a poem just comes out,
it seems even people who don't usually
write
can feel like they've expressed
something about themselves.
It seems as the case, without exception.
So this idea of these poetry generators
is unlocking poetry
and making it more accessible
to a broader audience, even in person.
A 1985 exhibition.
Same year again Kurosawa and Fujita Masaki
fictitious Museum of Lost and Found
was framed as a museum of artifacts
left behind by aliens,
which I wish I was around for.
This is sounds really cool,
including a perpetual poem
generating computer terminal.
That's one of the.
In 1987, Ito Takashi.
He imagined what a contemporary poetry
composition support system might be,
though he says he was kind of doing it
to make fun of other people
who are using computers
too much and writing poetry again.
1987 pretty early for this.
Gino, Toshi, Fumi.
He's looking at the current state
of contemporary poetry creation software
in 1995, and he used this as a way
to critique the state of poetry itself.
He says the actual poems being published
might as well be computer generated,
so why not just go the whole route
and just generate them ourselves?
In 1996, Tulsa, Norco,
Nakatsu
Ryohei came up with an interactive poem
interactive poem, which emerges
out of a conversation between
you and
a computerized amuse with this face
in which she composes
based on your emotional state
and you're ideally supposed to be
composing based on hers, like licking her
in the eyes, feeling what she's feeling,
and then composing back to her.
But I find this really terrifying.
So I'm going to move on.
And XO Nemo is another interesting one.
This is an internet
art duo symbol can scan a Kiowa
who gained this reputation of messing
with the digital and a lot of ways,
but they made one of Japan's first online
poem generators called BM 394.
And they have this sort of tongue in cheek
description on their page that is.
Sounds a lot like the press releases
of every AI company right now.
Quote the poetry
writing tool long awaited by poets,
copywriters, musicians and adventurers
in every expressive field is here.
Its name is BM 394 bio morph.
It is a poetry writing
formula support machine.
The M3 94 adopts a bio morph
type manipulation system,
allowing the user to create poems
far beyond their ability.
The operation is simple input an initial
word as the theme, and then just
select your favorite poem from the poems
randomly generated by the computer.
You will be how surprised
at how the bio morph based process creates
surprisingly brilliant poetry.
BM 394 at last, words
have their final weapon, so it's like
kind of like their anime villains
almost taking on that kind of rhetoric.
So I'm ending today in the 1990s,
but for later generators,
I'd also like to point the audience
to the renderings project
in the Electronic Literature Collection
three, which has my translation of Cino
Nomi 2012,
Contemporary Japanese Poetry Generator,
and my own 2014
bilingual Generative Poem or Automation.
But going through these examples
more than just emphasizing, hey,
Japan had poetry generators too,
though I also want to do that I aim.
What I aim to do today
is to give a sense of another history,
and another site of thinking
about generative poetics amid a discourse
and within a field of elit studies
still highly
dominated by a narrow slice of languages
and locales.
So, for example, if we take the examples
of haiku generation,
we can see how closely intertwined
Japanese poetics were
with even some of the earliest experiments
in generated literature
and the Japanese thinkers
who wrote about such experiments.
Also, we're exploring how a form
like haiku, one that inherently pushes
against historically dominant
Western ideas of what poetry is
and how it works
due to its extreme length constraints,
rejection of a lyrical subjectivity,
and even a centering of meaning,
a type of literature that,
even pre-digital, was seen as always,
inherently general.
We can point us to other value systems
when it comes to the confluence
of computation and writing.
On the other hand,
an oversize, simplistic,
oversimplified summary of such ideas
can itself fall into those
orientalist traps
I discussed at the beginning of this paper
into these maybe harmful ideas
about the general of Asia,
always imitating
and never imitating and always imitating,
but by juxtaposing these threads
along with this enormously rich history
of generative poetics in Japan.
I hope to show how much more interesting
and hard to sum up things actually are
and have been.
These aren't a final weapon, perhaps,
but to paraphrase
who I quoted earlier,
they leave open a generative space
where a strikingly vivid
wonder might still appear.
Thank you so much.